Louisiana Hayride Collection
Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division, Library of Congress
Louisiana hayride collection 1904-2006 1922-circa 1989
Kent, Joey
5 linear feet (10 boxes, approximately 4,375 items) various sizes
190 photographic prints some color 8 1/2 x 11 inches or smaller
110 negatives safety film 4 x 6 cm or smaller
over 200 sound recordings, including 7-inch analog sound tape reels and digital (DAT) sound cassettes; vinyl and shellac analog discs in various sizes and speeds (78, 45, and 33 1/3 rpm); and digital compact discs (CD and CD-R)
37 videocassettes, including 1/2-inch analog VHS and SVHS, and 1/4-inch digital DVCAM videocassettes
Recorded Sound Reference Center, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The collection documents radio history in Shreveport, Louisiana, with a special emphasis on the Louisiana Hayride country music program. Major topics include the earliest radio broadcasts in Shreveport, the founding and growth of KWKH radio under owner/broadcaster W.K. Henderson, and the legendary performances of the Louisiana Hayride program, which was broadcast live on KWKH radio from the Shreveport Municipal Auditorium. Manuscripts and photographs are available for research; sound and video recordings are still in process.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Bale, Norm.; Black, Bill, 1926-1965.; Cash, Johnny.; Fontana, D. J.; Fuhrman, Micki.; Henderson, William Kennon, b. 1880.; Horton, Johnny.; Kent, David, 1923-1992.; Kent, David, 1923-1992.; Kent, Joey.; Logan, Horace.; McEachern, Langston, 1918-2004.; Moore, Scotty.; Page, Frank.; Presley, Elvis, 1935-1977.; Williams, Hank, 1923-1953.
Organizations
KWKH (Radio station: Shreveport, La.)
Subjects
Country music radio stations--Louisiana--Shreveport.; Country music--Louisiana--Shreveport.; Honky-tonk music--Louisiana--Shreveport.; Radio--Louisiana--Shreveport.; Rockabilly music--Louisiana--Shreveport.
Places
Shreveport (La.)
Titles
Louisiana hayride (Radio program)
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Country music radio programs.; Group portraits.; Periodicals.; Photographic prints.; Portrait photographs.; Publicity photographs.; Safety film negatives.; Snapshots.
Occupations
Country musicians.; Disc jockeys.; Honky-tonk musicians.; Radio broadcasters.
Administrative Information
Collection Acquisition
The collection was purchased from Joey Kent of Shreveport, Louisiana, in 2009.
Additions
No further additions to the collection are expected.
Access Restrictions
Textual and graphic materials in the Louisiana Hayride Collection are open for research. Advance notice is required; contact a reference librarian in the Recorded Sound Reference Center, Library of Congress, Washington, DC, 20540-4690; (202) 707-7833.
The 203 sound recordings and 37 videocassettes that are also included in the collection are not yet available to researchers. Following preservation duplication and cataloging, the materials will be accessible through this finding guide and through the Library of Congress Online Catalog.
Administrative History
W.K. Henderson and KWKH Radio
The history of KWKH radio begins in 1922, when Shreveport, Louisiana, businessman William Kennon Henderson purchased a share of a small radio station from one of his employees, W.C. Patterson. The station initially was assigned the call numbers WGAQ and operated out of a studio in the Youree Hotel in Shreveport. In 1925 Henderson purchased a majority stake in WGAQ and relocated the station to his summer home, called Kennonwood, outside of Shreveport. Henderson also changed the call numbers to KWKH.
With KWKH up and running in Kennonwood, Henderson was eager to broadcast to a larger listening audience and began lobbying federal authorities for a more favorable wavelength and increased wattage. After these requests were denied in 1925, Henderson took matters into his own hands and increased KWKH's wattage without legal permission. This led to an investigation by Department of Commerce inspectors amid complaints from radio listeners across the country that KWKH was blocking reception of other programming.
During this time, Henderson began to use KWKH as a personal soapbox and gained a reputation for intensity and abrasiveness as he lambasted critics and accused the federal government of discriminating against the South. Behind the scenes, Henderson and his old partner, W.C. Patterson, sent out flurries of correspondence to U.S. senators, judges, the supervisor of radio in New Orleans, and even President Calvin Coolidge, continually requesting fair representation on the airwaves. Their crusade came to a crescendo in 1927 when, amid press coverage and a massive letter campaign, Henderson travelled to Washington to testify before the Federal Radio Commission. By the end of the decade, Henderson had secured his request to increase KWKH's power to 10,000 watts and successfully waged a legal campaign against an Oklahoma radio station, KVOO, that coveted KWKH's wavelength.
When Henderson wasn't waging legal battles, he was playing phonograph recordings and recruiting local talent to perform for his listeners. Eager to put a regional stamp on his broadcasts and support local music trends, he frequently played the "hillbilly" music that was popular in the area at the time. Henderson sold KWKH in 1932, but the seeds had been sown for the station to continue its support for the regional music that would so greatly influence the country and rockabilly genres.
The Louisiana Hayride
The Louisiana Hayride on KWKH radio began its primary run on April 3, 1948. Proclaiming itself the "Cradle of the Stars," the weekly radio program was broadcast live from the Shreveport Municipal Auditorium. The Hayride was one of several country and western style radio broadcasts that were popular at the time. What distinguished the Hayride was its willingness to branch into rockabilly and even early rock while providing a proving ground for young, aspiring, and often unknown artists. Indeed, the Hayride's raucous crowds and upstart musicians stood in stark contrast to the program's counterpart in Nashville, the Grand Ole Opry, which tapped into a more traditional and established line of country music performances.
Regular Hayride performers included country music legends, such as Hank Williams, Johnny Cash, Johnny Horton, Faron Young, George Jones, Merle Kilgore, Webb Pierce, the Maddox Brothers & Rose, David Houston, and the Wilburn Brothers, among others. In 1954 a teenaged Elvis Presley signed on as a regular Hayride cast member. Presley would perform at the Hayride weekly from 1954 until April 1956. By that time, his popularity had exploded far beyond the Hayride audience and he was permitted to buy out the remainder of his contract. However, KWKH and the Hayride, which by then broadcast at 50,000 watts to audiences throughout the country and beyond, played a critical role in launching the early career of the King of Rock and Roll.
Hosted through the years by Horace Logan, Frank Page, and Norm Bale, the Louisiana Hayride was broadcast weekly until 1960. Unfortunately, the once proud "Cradle of the Stars" had eroded as musicians fled to Nashville for more lucrative opportunities and the popularity of rock and roll increased. Programming continued sporadically throughout the sixties until 1974, when the Hayride was reborn for a thirteen-year run as a syndicated radio program under Shreveport businessman David Kent.
Sources:
Page, Frank, and Joey Kent. Elvis: the Hayride Years, 1954-1956. Parsippany, New Jersey: Louisiana Hayride, Inc., 2006.
Sterling, Christopher H., and Michael C. Keith. The Museum of Broadcast Communications Encyclopedia of Radio. Vol. 2, F-N. New York: Fitzroy Dearborn, 2004.
Scope and Contents
The collection predominantly covers early radio and television history in Shreveport, Louisiana; KWKH radio in the W.K. Henderson era; and the Louisiana Hayride years at KWKH radio. The Early Shreveport Radio and Television series provides special emphasis on the careers of Paul Carriger and William E. Antony (the latter was head engineer in the early days of WGAQ/KWKH). This is documented in ephemera, radio licenses, and published articles.
The KWKH Radio and W.K. Henderson series provides significant insight into early KWKH radio history and Henderson's personality and legal battles, as well as his financial struggles during the Great Depression. Several 78 rpm discs also document Henderson's original radio broadcasts. Ephemera relating to the Henderson Iron Works and early KWKH radio is of particular interest.
The KWKH Radio and the Louisiana Hayride series contains original program notes, posters, postcards, and ephemera related to Hayride performances. A group of tape reels in this series documents a sampling of live Louisiana Hayride performances from 1956-1961. Several LP and 78 rpm commercial recordings feature Louisiana Hayride performances from the primary and secondary runs. There are also over thirty transcription discs from the Hayrides's years as a syndicated radio program. There are also photographic prints (including some contacts prints and sheets) and negatives showing performers during the program's initial and secondary runs. A number of the photographs were taken by longtime Shreveport Times photographer Langston McEachern.
A separate series related to Elvis Presley's time at the Hayride is notable for its photographs of Presley at the Shreveport Municipal Auditorium, both in performance on stage and interacting with staff and fans backstage.
Three additional series feature collection documentation prepared by the donor; a list of periodicals relating to radio enthusiasts, country music, and Shreveport life; and a group of songbooks and sheet music.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 7 series:
Series 1: Early Shreveport Radio and Television, 1922-1964
Series 2: KWKH Radio and W.K. Henderson, 1904-1998, bulk 1922-1939, undated
Series 3: KWKH Radio and the Louisiana Hayride, 1942-2005
Series 4: Elvis Presley and the Louisiana Hayride, 1956-1994
Series 5: Radio and Country Music Periodicals and Publications, 1916-2003
Series 6: Songbooks and Sheet Music, 1931-1948, undated
Series 7: Accompanying Descriptive Documentation, 1956-1987, undated
http://lccn.loc.gov/2011622950
Container List
- Series 1. Early Shreveport Radio and Television, 1922-1964, undated
  Series 1 includes correspondence, licenses, listener verification requests, and ephemera from various early Shreveport, Louisiana, radio and television stations (KTSL, KGDX, WDAN, KWEA, and W5XA). Also included are handwritten research timelines and notations as well as photocopies of various publications relevant to the period. The material especially emphasizes the work of Paul Carriger and William E. Antony, early radio and television broadcasters in Shreveport.
  Materials in this series are predominantly reproductions.
  Materials were arranged chronologically within content groupings when dates were available.
  - Correspondence, 1922-1933 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Charters and licenses, 1922-1933 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Shortwave radio listener (DXer's) verification requests, 1931-1932, undated (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Ephemera, circa 1927-1933, undated (Box-folder 1/4)
    Includes an original 1931 W5XA postcard showing Giddens Castle, a Shreveport, Louisiana, landmark, built by Tandy Key Giddens, that housed early Shreveport radio and television stations. Also included are reproductions documenting program information, broadcast and frequency information, first-hand accounts of Paul Carriger's and William E. Antony's early radio and television broadcasting experiences, and a description of Giddens Castle.
  - Articles and publications, 1922-1964, bulk 1922, undated (Box-folder 1/5)
    Includes numerous newspaper article photocopies from 1922 and several pages from the December 1931 issue of Waves from the Castle of Dreams. A 1964 article and two undated articles document the lives and experiences of William E. Antony and Paul Carriger.
  - Research timelines and notations, undated (Box-folder 1/6)
    Includes handwritten timelines and notations documenting call letters, frequencies, wattage allotments, sale and purchase information, and radio equipment for early radio stations in the Shreveport, Louisiana, area.
- Series 2. KWKH Radio and W.K. Henderson, 1904-1998, bulk 1922-1939, undated
  Series 2 includes licenses, broadcast transcripts, newspaper and magazine articles, and ephemera relating to KWKH radio from the time of its founding by W.C. Patterson to its subsequent ownership by W.K. Henderson. Correspondence, articles and publications, and newspaper photocopies provide a vivid account of the legal disputes that highlighted Henderson's career as KWKH owner and broadcaster. These relate especially to the crusade to increase the station's wattage and wavelength frequency. Anti-chain store publications reflect Henderson's strong support of locally owned businesses in Shreveport, Louisiana. Materials in the correspondence files; congressional and Federal Radio Commission records; legal documentation; and files containing licenses, transcripts, chain store booklets, and newspaper articles are predominantly reproductions.
  - Correspondence, 1922-1938
    - 1922-1926 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - 1927-1938 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Congressional and Federal Radio Commission records, 1927-1933 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Legal documentation, 1929-1939 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Licenses, 1926-1936 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Transcripts, 1935-1937 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Ephemera, 1904-1985, bulk 1929-1932 (Box-folder 1/13)
    Includes clippings, advertisements, programs, logs, and other assorted material related to KWKH during the W.K. Henderson era. Notable materials include original W.K. Henderson commentaries and transcripts printed in local newspapers, a miniature pilot's log of the KWKH airplane, an illustration showing Chief Kiutus Tecumseh, a map and published images of the Henderson Iron Works, and official advertisements for KWKH radio on local programs and publications. All items are originals.
    - Map of Henderson Iron Works, Shreveport, Louisiana, 1904
    - Radio Digest clippings, 1926 January 2 (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Radiologue clipping, 1929 February 17 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Chain store booklets, undated (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Articles and publications, 1925-1998, undated (Box-folder 1/15-16)
    Includes an issue of Shreveport Magazine, June 1925; an article from Shreveport Magazine, November 1979; and an article from The Shreveport Journal, June 28, 1985. Two especially important historical sources included here are Hello World Henderson: the Man Behind the Mike by Margery Land May, 1930, and a first-hand account by W.K. Henderson titled The Story of KWKH, Shreveport, Louisiana.
  - Newspaper photocopies, 1914-1952
    - 1914-1924 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - 1926-1927 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - 1929 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - 1930 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - 1931, 1935-1952 (Box-folder 2/5)
- Series 3. KWKH Radio and the Louisiana Hayride, 1942-2005
  Series 3 documents the Louisiana Hayride era at KWKH radio. This series is rich in original material, including photographs, reproductions and illustrations, correspondence, articles and clippings, posters, postcards, programs, and ephemera. A notable subseries includes photocopied, handwritten Louisiana Hayride program notes with performer lists, song titles, and limited commentary. There are also several folders of photocopied newspaper advertisements from this era at KWKH radio.
  - Correspondence, 1956-2004 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Articles and clippings, 1946-2005, undated (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Postcards, 1942-1960 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Posters, 1944, 1951-1987, undated
    - 1951-1987, undated (Box-folder 2/9)
    - 1944, undated (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Programs, 1950-1974, undated (Box-folder 2/10-11)
    Some programs include performer autographs.
  - Ephemera, 1948-1972, undated
    Includes KWKH administrative documentation, memorabilia, and an assortment of peripheral material associated with the radio station and its history. Notable items include a KWKH listener appreciation concert ticket stub, a group of official KWKH EKKO radio reception stamps, and a small notebook with autographs of several early Louisiana Hayride performers.
    - Ephemera, 1948-1972, undated (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Polly Waldron's Open House Cook Book, 1962 August (Box 7)
  - Program notes, 1954-1957
    - 1954 (Box-folder 2/13)
    - 1955 (Box-folder 2/14)
    - 1956 (Box-folder 2/15)
    - 1957 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Newspaper advertisements, 1960-1967
    Photocopies.
    - 1960-1963 (Box-folder 2/17)
    - 1964-1967 (Box-folder 2/18)
    - Johnny Cash advertisement, The Billboard's Popularity Charts, 1956 July 7 (Box-folder 8/3)
    - The Louisiana Hayride: the glory years, 1948-60: a compilation of newspaper articles, pictures, and advertisements, compiled by Robert Gentry, 1998 (Box 10)
  - Photographs, 1942–circa 1980s, undated
    - Louisiana Hayride, primary run, 1926, 1942-1969, undated
      Photographs predominantly show performers and hosts from the Louisiana Hayride country music show. Also represented are various individuals and events associated with this period of KWKH radio history.
      - Individual performers and performing groups, 1942, 1950-1969, undated
        Publicity photographs, snapshots, and performance images.
        - Gene Autry at Municipal Auditorium, 1951, LSU-Shreveport Archives; 1 photographic print: black and white; 10 x 8 inches; RS 13857 P1 (Box-folder 9/1)
        - Linda Brannon performing on stage at the Louisiana Hayride, 1958, 1 photographic print: black and white; 5 x 3 1/2 inches; RS 13857 P2 (Box-folder 9/1)
          Autographed.
        - Johnny Cash photographs, circa late 1950s–1969
          - Johnny Cash and Johnny Horton, circa late 1950s, 2 photographic prints: black and white; 8 x 10 inches and 10 x 8 inches; RS 13857 P3; RS 13857 P4 (Box-folder 9/1)
            One of the photographs is credited to Graham's Studio, Shreveport.
            For additional photographs of Johnny Horton, see also Johnny Horton photographs, circa 1954-1960
          - Johnny Cash with unidentified man at the Louisiana State Fair, 1969, Paul Ambrico Photography; 1 photographic print: color; 10 x 8 inches; RS 13857 P5 (Box-folder 9/1)
        - Jimmie Davis photographs, circa 1926-1929, 1942
          - Professor J.H. Davis, Dodd College portrait photograph, between 1926 and 1929, 1 photographic print: black and white; 3 1/2 x 3 inches; RS 13857 P6 (Box-folder 9/1)
            Davis taught history and social studies at the Dodd College for Girls in Shreveport for one year in the late 1920s.
          - Jimmie Davis in performance at KWKH, 1942, 1 photographic print: black and white; 10 x 8 inches; RS 13857 P7 (Box-folder 9/1)
          - Louisiana governor Jimmie Davis sits at a piano while Norm Bale, [Horace Logan?], and a group of musicians look on, at Davis's home, 1953, Film Arbor Studio; 1 photographic print: black and white; 8 x 10 inches; RS 13857 P8 (Box-folder 9/1)
            For additional photographs of Norm Bale, see also Norm Bale photographs, 1950s
        - Sonny Frommel, Ray Leckie, Dickie French, Fats Povis, and Frankie Miller posing with their instruments, California, 1952, 1 photographic print: black and white; 8 x 10 inches; RS 13857 P9 (Box-folder 9/2)
          Handwritten on back of photographic print: "The band Sonny and I played with when we were in the army."
        - Harold Gay, Frankie Miller, and Felton Pruitt performing on stage, circa 1960, Graham's Studio, Shreveport, Louisiana; 1 photographic print: black and white; 10 x 8 inches; RS 13857 P10 (Box-folder 9/2)
        - Dale Hawkins performing on stage, 1958, LSU Shreveport Archives; 1 photographic print: black and white; 10 x 8 inches; RS 13857 P11 (Box-folder 9/2)
        - Tommy Hill, Hank Williams, "Socko" Sokolowski, and Johnny Horton, 1949-1953, 1 photographic print: black and white; 5 x 3 1/2 inches; RS 13857 P12 (Box-folder 9/2)
          For additional photographs of Hank Williams, see also Hank Williams photographs, 1952, undated. For additional photographs of Johnny Horton, see also Johnny Horton photographs, circa 1954-1960
        - Johnny Horton photographs, circa 1954-1960
          see also Johnny Cash and Johnny Horton, circa late 1950s and Tommy Hill, Hank Williams, "Socko" Sokolowski, and Johnny Horton, 1949-1953
          - Johnny Horton and Frank Page snapshot, circa 1954-1960, 1 photographic print: color; 3 1/2 x 3 1/2 inches; RS 13857 P13 (Box-folder 9/2)
            For additional photographs of Frank Page, see also Frank Page with Louisiana Hayride performers and hosts, [between 1948 and 1958?]
          - Johnny Horton portrait snapshots, circa 1954-1960, 2 photographic prints: color; 3 1/2 x 3 1/2 inches and 3 1/4 x 4 1/2 inches; RS 13857 P14; RS 13857 P15 (Box-folder 9/2)
          - Johnny Horton seated in automobile, [between 1955 and 1960?], 1 photographic print: color; 11 x 8 1/2 inches; RS 13857 P16 (Box-folder 9/2)
            Duplicate of original photographic print with handwriting on front: "His car he was killed in, November 5th, 1960."
            This image appears on the cover of Horton's album Done Rovin' (Briar 104, 1966).
          - Johnny Horton portrait photograph with mirror, circa 1954-1960, 1 photographic print: black and white; 11 x 8 1/2 inches; RS 13857 P17 (Box-folder 9/3)
            Autographed on front of photograph (quoting the song "Done Rovin'" from the Horton single (Cormac 1193, 1951) and album of the same title): "To Mom and Dad, I'm 'Done Rovin' down that lonesome road. Love & kisses, Johnny Horton."
          - Johnny Horton portrait photograph with guitar, circa 1954-1960, 1 photographic print: black and white; 8 1/2 x 11 inches; RS 13857 P18 (Box-folder 9/3)
          - Johnny Horton and unidentified woman, circa 1954-1960, 1 photographic print: black and white; 10 x 8 inches; RS 13857 P19 (Box-folder 9/3)
          - Johnny Horton performing on stage at the Louisiana Hayride, circa 1954-1960, McEachern, Langston, 1918-2004; 1 photographic print: black and white; 8 x 10 inches; RS 13857 P20 (Box-folder 9/3)
        - David Houston and sixteen-year-old James Burton performing on stage at the Louisiana Hayride, 1956, McEachern, Langston, 1918-2004; 1 photographic print: black and white; 10 x 8 inches; RS 13857 P21 (Box-folder 9/3)
          Autographed on front by James Burton: "To Joey [Kent]. Peace & [illegible]. God bless."
          For additional photographs of James Burton, see also Concert to celebrate the 50th anniversary of Elvis Presley's first appearance on the Louisiana Hayride, at the Municipal Auditorium, Shreveport, 2004 October 16
        - Van Howard publicity photographs, circa 1950-1956, 3 photographic prints: black and white; 10 x 8 inches and 5 x 3 inches; RS 13857 P22–RS 13857 P24 (Box-folder 9/3)
        - Louisiana Hayride cast on stage, 1954 August 15, undated, McEachern, Langston, 1918-2004; 2 photographic prints: black and white; 8 x 10 inches; RS 13857 P25; RS 13857 P25 (copy 2) (Box-folder 9/4)
          Attached to the KWKH Louisiana Hayride banner above the stage is a smaller banner advertising Tube Rose Snuff, Brown & Williamson Tobacco Co.
        - Louisiana Hayride cast on stage, 1958, 3 photographic prints: black and white; 5 x 7 inches; RS 13857 P26–RS 13857 P27 (copy 2) (Box-folder 9/4)
          Two of the photographic prints are duplicates.